<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Ecodemography | Will Petry</title>
    <link>http://wpetry.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Ecodemography | Will Petry</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 William Petry</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://wpetry.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How many Switzerlands is a California?</title>
      <link>http://wpetry.github.io/post/howmanyswitzerlands/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wpetry.github.io/post/howmanyswitzerlands/</guid>
      <description>Overview elide offers tools to manipulate Spatial* objects of all types to compare unfamiliar spatial extents to more familiar benchmarks. This tutorial shows how to use this function to make compelling visual comparisons.
Featured skills:
 elide to move, rotate, and scale Spatial* objects
 aggregating polygons
 calculating new polygons from overlapping polygons
 calculating global and regional centroids
 plotting spatial data with ggplot2
  UPDATE (September 2017): The sf package has been developed to allow better integration of spatial data with the tidyverse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate effects on structured populations</title>
      <link>http://wpetry.github.io/post/tempdemog/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wpetry.github.io/post/tempdemog/</guid>
      <description>[Start playing with the R Shiny app or download the source files from my GitHub to run it locally in RStudio]
This interactive model—developed with Chris Johnson—projects the population dynamics a simple organism that has two temperature-sensitive life stages, a juvenile and an adult. We might choose such a model for organisms like frogs (tadpoles/adults), insects (larvae/adults), or other poikilothermic ectotherm. The model assumes that each stage has an optimal temperature for its various life history functions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Illuminating the world&#39;s demographic dark corners</title>
      <link>http://wpetry.github.io/post/demogdarkcorners/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wpetry.github.io/post/demogdarkcorners/</guid>
      <description>[Originally posted on the COM(P)ADRE blog on 28 April 2017]
When I first downloaded COMPADRE mere moments after it went public, I was attending the EvoDemoS meeting at Stanford; we were less than 60 km from the nearest matrix population model in the database (Calochortus tiburonensis; Fiedler 1987). My Ph.D. fieldwork brought me considerably closer, and not just because I worked with historic matrix population models collected near the field station.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World!</title>
      <link>http://wpetry.github.io/post/helloworld/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wpetry.github.io/post/helloworld/</guid>
      <description>In the spirit of open data, I&amp;rsquo;ve moved towards posting the raw data and code that underlie my science (see here, here, and here for recent examples). Occaisionally I work on small side projects that make for neat stories, but don&amp;rsquo;t always make it to a publication. Here is where I&amp;rsquo;ll post short write ups that highlight ideas and data analysis tools.
Hardly regular, hopefully somewhat original&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>