<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Communities on Ecodemography | Will Petry</title>
    <link>http://wpetry.github.io/tags/communities/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Communities on Ecodemography | Will Petry</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 William Petry</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://wpetry.github.io/tags/communities/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Maintenance of biodiversity</title>
      <link>http://wpetry.github.io/project/biodiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wpetry.github.io/project/biodiversity/</guid>
      <description>How do so many types of organisms persist on a small number of shared resources? Organisms compete with their neighbors&amp;ndash;both individuals of the same and different species–-for resources. Through recent theoretical and empirical advances, we&amp;rsquo;ve come to understand the mechanisms that maintain the incredible diversity of species that we observe in competitive communities. However, these competitor species are themselves resources for consumers, and many hypotheses for the origin of diversity depend.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Globally-distributed ecology</title>
      <link>http://wpetry.github.io/project/distecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wpetry.github.io/project/distecology/</guid>
      <description>[Dummy caterpillar at Zackenberg, Greenland (photo: Tomas Roslin)]
Process-level ecological data is usually collected locally, making scaling to the landscape and global scale a dubious exercise. I&amp;rsquo;m collborating with two projects that seek to remedy this deficiency by using global distributed experiments.
Geographic gradients in species interactions Species diversity generally increases towards the Equator, and the extent to which this affects species interactions will have profound biogeographic and evolutionary consequences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drivers of species interactions</title>
      <link>http://wpetry.github.io/project/interactiondrivers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://wpetry.github.io/project/interactiondrivers/</guid>
      <description>Temporal dynamics of species interaction networks Make a list of species that occur in a given place, and only a fraction of the potential interaction links between species will ever occur. Building and analyzing these interaction networks has substantially advanced our understanding of community structure, function, and stability. Because the forces that control species&amp;rsquo; abundances and behaviors, it follows that these links&amp;ndash;and their ecological and evolutionary consequences&amp;ndash;may vary in space and time.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>